in this video we're going to talk about
how to calculate the sound intensity
level in decibels
so here's a good example
we're given the intensity of a sound
wave how can we find the intensity level
so here's the formula that you need
the decibels is equal to 10
times log
of the intensity
divided by the threshold of intensity or
the threshold of hearing
so the lowest intensity that can be
picked up by our ears
is 1 times 10 to the minus 12
watts per square meter
so that's basically the reference value
so now to calculate the intensity level
is going to be 10
times log
of this intensity value
divided by the threshold of hearing
so if you type in log four times ten to
the minus five divided by one times ten
to minus twelve
that's seven point six
multiplied by ten
so the sound level
is seventy six decibels
and so that's a simple way to calculate
the sound level given the intensity of a
sound wave
now what if we're given the sound level
in decibels and we'll need to calculate
the intensity
but we'll need to rearrange the formula
so let's start with this equation
our goal is to solve for that variable
so the first thing we need to do is
divide both sides by 10.
so the sound level
divided by 10
that's going to equal log
of the intensity divided by the
threshold of
hearing now the next thing that we need
to do is convert the logarithmic
equation
into an exponential equation
and so let me give an example of that
let's say if we have log base a
of b is equal to c
it turns out that a
raised to the c
is equal to b
so the base of log is base 10
so 10
raised to b over 10 is equal to what's
inside
so the stuff inside i
over the threshold of hearing is going
to be equal to 10
raised to the
sound level divided by 10.
now the last thing we need to do is
multiply both sides by
i naught
so the intensity
is the threshold of hearing
times 10
raised to the sound level divided by 10.
so now we can get the answer so it's
going to be 1 times 10 to the minus 12
multiplied by 10
raised to the 50 divided by 10.
so 50 over 10 is 5 so it's 10 to the 5
multiplied by 1 times 10 to the minus
12.
so the intensity is going to be 1 times
10 to the minus 7
watts per square meter
so that corresponds to a sound level of
50 decibels
now what about a sound level of 60
decibels
so it's going to be 1 times 10 to the
minus 12.
times ten but
sixty over ten
so the intensity is going to be
one times ten to the minus 6 watts
so that corresponds to a sound level of
60 decibels
so notice when the sound level
increased by 10 units
so when we add 10 decibels to go from 50
to 60 decibels
the intensity
change from 10 to the minus 6
actually 10 to the minus 7
to 10 to the minus 6. so it was
increased by a factor of ten
so notice that an addition of ten
decibel units
increase
the intensity
by a multiplication of ten
make sure you understand that every time
the decimal factor or the sound level
increases by 10 decibels
the intensity
gets multiplied by 10 is 10 times higher
than what it was before
let's move on to number three
the sound level is 40 decibels at 2
meters from the source
what is the sound level in decibels at 4
so let's say if we have a speaker
so at a distance of 2 meters
it's 40 decibels
what's going to happen
to the sound level
if we double the distance
what's the new sound level going to be
well let's come up with an equation
that's going to help us to get that
answer
so we know that
intensity
is i naught times 10
raised to b over 10.
and also intensity
is power divided by area and this is the
surface area of a sphere
so we need to connect
the distance which is basically r
with the decibel levels which is b
or beta
how can we connect these two together
well first let's find the ratio
of intensities
so i2 is going to be p
over 4 pi
r2 squared
and i1 is going to be p over 4 pi
r1 squared
so since we're dealing with the same
source it's going to emit the same power
and 4 pi is the same
so i2 divided by i1
is going to be 1 over
r2 squared divided by 1 over r1 squared
now i'm going to multiply the top
and the bottom by
r1 squared
times r2 squared
whatever you do to the top we must also
do to the bottom
so that the value of the fraction
remains the same so these will cancel
so r1 squared is going to be on the top
and r2 squared is going to be on the
bottom
so i2 over i1
is going to be r1 squared divided by r2
squared
now let's focus on this equation
so once again let's take the ratio of
two intensities
so i2 is going to be i not times 10
beta 2 over 10
and i1 is going to be i zero times 10
beta 1 over 10.
so we could cancel these two
now when you're dividing using a common
base you need to subtract the exponents
for example x to the seven divided by x
to the third
is x to the seven minus three or x to
the fourth
so this is going to be b 2 over 10 minus
b 1 over 10.
so we can say that i 2 over i 1
is equal to 10
b 2
over 10 minus b 1 over 10 which because
they have the same denominator we could
simply say it's just
b two minus b one over ten
so now
we could set
this term
equal to that because they both equal i2
over i1
so r1 squared over r2 squared
is equal to 10
b2 minus b1
over 10.
so now what we need to do is take the
log of both sides
so log
r1 squared over r2 squared
is equal to log
b2 minus b1
over 10.
now a property of logs allows you to
take the exponent and move it to the
front for example
log x squared
is the same as 2 log x
you could take the 2 and move it to the
front
so therefore we could take this term
move it here
so on the left we have log
r1 over r2 and i'm just going to put the
square on the outside which is
equivalently equal to that
and this is equal to b2 minus b1
over 10
times log 10.
log 10 is 1 so we don't have to worry
about this thing and i'm going to move
this 2 to the front
so now i have 2 log
r1 divided by r2
and that's equal to b2 minus b1 over 10.
so i'm going to multiply both sides by
10.
so on this side all i have is b2
minus b1
and on the left side i have 10 times 2
which is 20
times log
r1 divided by r2
so now i just got to add b1 to both
sides
so b2
is equal to b1
plus 20
log r1 divided by r2
so that's how i can calculate the new
intensity level
at a different distance
so in this example b1
is 40 decibels
and that corresponds to a distance of 2
meters our goal is to look for b2
when the distance doubles to 4 meters
so let's go ahead and find our answer
b1 is 40
and then it's going to be plus 20
log r1 which is 2 and r2 is 4.
so log 2 divided by 4
that's negative 0.301 and then multiply
that by 20 and so this is going to be 40
minus 6.02
and so beta2
is 33.98
decibels
so that's how you can calculate the new
sound level
at
a different distance
you